I'd like to start with a simple question:
أود أن أبدأ بسؤالٍ بسيط:
Why do the poor make so many poor decisions?
لم يتخذ الفقراء العديد من القرارات السيئة؟
I know it's a harsh question,
أعرف بأنه سؤالٌ قاسٍ،
but take a look at the data.
لكن لنلق نظرة على البيانات.
The poor borrow more, save less,
يستدين الفقراء أكثر بينما يدّخرون أقل،
smoke more, exercise less, drink more
يدخنون أكثر ويمارسون الرياضة أقل، يشربون أكثر
and eat less healthfully.
ويأكلون بشكلٍ صحيٍ أقل.
Why?
لماذا؟
Well, the standard explanation
حسناً، التفسير الاعتيادي لهذا
was once summed up by the British Prime Minister, Margaret Thatcher.
لخصته رئيسة الوزراء البريطانية مارغريت ثاتشر
And she called poverty "a personality defect."
وأسمت الفقر "عيباً في الشخصية."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
A lack of character, basically.
نقص في الشخصية، بشكل رئيسي.
Now, I'm sure not many of you would be so blunt.
أعرف أن معظمكم ليس بهذه القسوة.
But the idea that there's something wrong with the poor themselves
لكن فكرة أن هناك خطأً في الفقراء أنفسهم
is not restricted to Mrs. Thatcher.
لا تقتصر على السيدة ثاتشر.
Some of you may believe that the poor should be held responsible
قد يعتقد بعضكم أن على الفقراء تحمل مسؤولية
for their own mistakes.
أخطائهم.
And others may argue that we should help them to make better decisions.
ويرى البعض الآخر أنه علينا مساعدتهم لاتخاذ قرارات أفضل.
But the underlying assumption is the same:
ولكن الافتراض الأساسي هو نفسه:
there's something wrong with them.
هناك شيء خاطئ فيهم.
If we could just change them,
لو كان بمقدورنا فقط تغييرهم،
if we could just teach them how to live their lives,
لو كان بمقدورنا فقط تعليمهم كيف يجب أن يعيشوا حياتهم،
if they would only listen.
لو أنّهم يستمعون.
And to be honest,
ولأكون صريحاً معكم،
this was what I thought for a long time.
هذا ما فكرت به لمدة طويلة.
It was only a few years ago that I discovered
لكن اكتشفت منذ عدّة سنوات
that everything I thought I knew about poverty was wrong.
أنّ كل ما ظننت أني أعرفه عن الفقر كان خطأ.
It all started when I accidentally stumbled upon a paper
بدأت القصة عندما عثرت مصادفة على بحث
by a few American psychologists.
لمجموعة من علماء نفس أمريكيين.
They had traveled 8,000 miles, all the way to India,
كانوا قد سافروا مسافة 8000 ميلاً إلى الهند
for a fascinating study.
للقيام بدراسة رائعة.
And it was an experiment with sugarcane farmers.
وقد كانت تجربة مع مزارعي قصب السكر.
You should know that these farmers collect about 60 percent
يجب أن تعرف أن هؤلاء المزارعين يجمعون حوالي 60 بالمئة
of their annual income all at once,
من دخلهم السنوي في وقت واحد،
right after the harvest.
مباشرة بعد الحصاد.
This means that they're relatively poor one part of the year
هذا يعني أنهم فقراء نسبياً في بعض فترات السنة.
and rich the other.
وأغنياء في فترات أخرى.
The researchers asked them to do an IQ test before and after the harvest.
طلب منهم الباحثون أن يقوموا باختبار ذكاء قبل وبعد الحصاد.
What they subsequently discovered completely blew my mind.
وما اكتشفوه لاحقاً أذهلني تماماً.
The farmers scored much worse on the test before the harvest.
كانت نتائج المزارعين أسوأ بكثير قبل الحصاد
The effects of living in poverty, it turns out,
وقد اتّضح أنّ آثار المعيشة في الفقر
correspond to losing 14 points of IQ.
يقابلها فقدان 14 نقطة في اختبار الذكاء.
Now, to give you an idea,
لأعطيكم فكرة أوضح،
that's comparable to losing a night's sleep
هذا ما يعادل السهر لليلةٍ كاملة
or the effects of alcoholism.
أو آثار الإدمان على الكحول.
A few months later, I heard that Eldar Shafir,
بعد بضعة أشهر، سمعت أن إلدر شافير،
a professor at Princeton University and one of the authors of this study,
أستاذ في جامعة برنستون وأحد باحثي هذه الدراسة،
was coming over to Holland, where I live.
كان سيأتي إلى هولندا، حيث أعيش.
So we met up in Amsterdam
لذلك التقينا في أمستردام
to talk about his revolutionary new theory of poverty.
للحديث عن نظريته الثورية الجديدة حول الفقر.
And I can sum it up in just two words:
ويمكنني أن ألخصها بكلمتين فقط:
scarcity mentality.
عقلية الحاجة.
It turns out that people behave differently
فقد اتضح بأن الناس يتصرفون بشكل مختلف
when they perceive a thing to be scarce.
عندما يدركون أن شيئاً ما ينقصهم
And what that thing is doesn't much matter --
بصرف النظر عما هو هذا الشيء --
whether it's not enough time, money or food.
سواء كان لا يوجد ما يكفي من الوقت أو المال أو الطعام.
You all know this feeling,
جميعكم تعرفون هذا الشعور،
when you've got too much to do,
عندما يكون لديك الكثير لتقوم به،
or when you've put off breaking for lunch
أو عندما تؤجل استراحة الغداء
and your blood sugar takes a dive.
وينخفض عندها مستوى سكر الدم.
This narrows your focus to your immediate lack --
هذا ما يحصر تركيزك على حاجتك المباشرة --
to the sandwich you've got to have now,
الشطيرة التي يجب أن تتناولها الآن،
the meeting that's starting in five minutes
الاجتماع الذي سيبدأ خلال خمس دقائق،
or the bills that have to be paid tomorrow.
أو الفواتير الواجب تسديدها في الغد.
So the long-term perspective goes out the window.
بالنتيجة، سيختفي المنظور طويل الأمد.
You could compare it to a new computer
بإمكانك مقارنة هذا بجهاز حاسوب جديد
that's running 10 heavy programs at once.
يقوم بتشغيل 10 برامج ثقيلة في آن واحد.
It gets slower and slower, making errors.
سيبدأ بالتباطؤ، ومن ثم يقوم بالأخطاء.
Eventually, it freezes --
في نهاية المطاف، سيتوقف --
not because it's a bad computer,
ليس لأنه جهاز سيء،
but because it has too much to do at once.
لكن عليه إنجاز كثير من المهام في آن واحد.
The poor have the same problem.
يعاني الفقراء من نفس المشكلة.
They're not making dumb decisions because they are dumb,
قراراتهم الغبيّة ليست نتيجة غبائهم،
but because they're living in a context
ولكنها نتيجة عيشهم ضمن سياق
in which anyone would make dumb decisions.
قد يقود أي شخص لاتخاذ قرارات غبيّة.
So suddenly I understood
أدركت فجأة
why so many of our anti-poverty programs don't work.
لم لا تنجح الكثير من برامج مكافحة الفقر لدينا
Investments in education, for example, are often completely ineffective.
مثلاً، غالباً ما تكون استثمارات التعليم بلا نتيجة.
Poverty is not a lack of knowledge.
الفقر ليس نقصاً في المعرفة.
A recent analysis of 201 studies
في تحليل حديث مكون من 201 دراسة
on the effectiveness of money-management training
حول فعالية التدريب على إدارة المال،
came to the conclusion that it has almost no effect at all.
تظهر النتيجة أنه تقريباً بدون فعالية.
Now, don't get me wrong --
لا تسيؤوا فهمي --
this is not to say the poor don't learn anything --
فأنا لا أعني أن الفقراء لا يتعلمون شيئاً--
they can come out wiser for sure.
بالتأكيد يمكنهم أن يصبحوا أذكى.
But it's not enough.
لكن هذا لا يكفي.
Or as Professor Shafir told me,
أو كما قال لي الأستاذ شافير،
"It's like teaching someone to swim
"هذا أشبه بتعليم السباحة لأحد ما،
and then throwing them in a stormy sea."
ومن ثم رميه في بحر هائج."
I still remember sitting there,
لازلت أذكر كيف جلست هناك،
perplexed.
حائراً
And it struck me
وقد صدمني
that we could have figured this all out decades ago.
كيف كان بإمكاننا استنتاج كلّ هذا منذ عقود.
I mean, these psychologists didn't need any complicated brain scans;
أعني أن هؤلاء العلماء لم يحتاجوا لعمليات مسح دماغ معقدة.
they only had to measure the farmer's IQ,
كان عليهم فقط قياس معدل ذكاء المزارعين،
and IQ tests were invented more than 100 years ago.
واختبارات الذكاء موجودة من أكثر من 100 عام
Actually, I realized I had read about the psychology of poverty before.
في الواقع، لقد أدركت بأنه سبق لي وقرأت عن علم نفس الفقر.
George Orwell, one of the greatest writers who ever lived,
جورج أورويل، أحد أعظم الكتاب في التاريخ
experienced poverty firsthand in the 1920s.
عاش بفقر لفترة زمنية بشكل مباشر في عشرينيات القرن الماضي.
"The essence of poverty," he wrote back then,
كتب حينها "جوهر الفقر"
is that it "annihilates the future."
هو أنه "يلغي المستقبل."
And he marveled at, quote,
وكان يتعجب
"How people take it for granted they have the right to preach at you
"كيف يعتبر الناس أن لديهم الحق الطبيعي بأن يعظوك
and pray over you
ويصلوا لأجلك
as soon as your income falls below a certain level."
حالما يصبح دخلك أدنى من مستوى معين."
Now, those words are every bit as resonant today.
لا يزال وقع هذه الكلمات قوياً حتى يومنا هذا
The big question is, of course:
يبقى السؤال الأهم بالطبع:
What can be done?
ما الذي يمكن فعله؟
Modern economists have a few solutions up their sleeves.
يحتفظ علماء الاقتصاد المعاصرين ببعض الحلول في جعبتهم.
We could help the poor with their paperwork
يمكننا مساعدة الفقراء بأعمالهم الورقية
or send them a text message to remind them to pay their bills.
أو إرسال رسائل نصية لهم لتذكيرهم بدفع فواتيرهم.
This type of solution is hugely popular with modern politicians,
هذا النوع من الحلول شائع جداً لدى السياسيين المعاصرين،
mostly because,
والسبب الرئيسي،
well, they cost next to nothing.
أنّ تكلفته لا تذكر.
These solutions are, I think, a symbol of this era
برأيي، هذه النوعية من الحلول تمثل الفترة الحالية
in which we so often treat the symptoms,
حيث نلجأ معظم الأحيان لعلاج الأعراض
but ignore the underlying cause.
في حين نتجاهل المسبب الرئيسي.
So I wonder:
لذلك أتساءل:
Why don't we just change the context in which the poor live?
لما لا نقوم فقط بتغيير الواقع الذي يعيش فيه الفقراء؟
Or, going back to our computer analogy:
أو، بالعودة لمثالنا على جهاز الحاسوب،
Why keep tinkering around with the software
لماذا نعبث ببرنامجه الإلكتروني
when we can easily solve the problem by installing some extra memory instead?
في حين أنه يمكننا حل المشكلة بسهولة عبر إلحاق ذاكرة إضافية؟
At that point, Professor Shafir responded with a blank look.
هنا أجاب الأستاذ شافير بنظرة جامدة.
And after a few seconds, he said,
وبعد عدة ثوانٍ قال،
"Oh, I get it.
"آه، فهمت.
You mean you want to just hand out more money to the poor
تعني أنك تريد أن يحصل الفقراء على مال أكثر
to eradicate poverty.
للقضاء على الفقر.
Uh, sure, that'd be great.
سيكون هذا أمراً رائعاً بالطبع.
But I'm afraid that brand of left-wing politics
لكن أخشى أن جماعة السياسيين اليساريين
you've got in Amsterdam --
الموجودة عندكم في أمستردام --
it doesn't exist in the States."
هي غير موجودة في الولايات المتحدة."
But is this really an old-fashioned, leftist idea?
لكن هل هذه فعلاً فكرة يسارية تقليدية؟
I remembered reading about an old plan --
تذكرت أني سبق وقرأت عن خطة قديمة --
something that has been proposed by some of history's leading thinkers.
شيء كان قد طرحه من قبل أبرز المفكرين في التاريخ.
The philosopher Thomas More first hinted at it in his book, "Utopia,"
والفيلسوف توماس مور كان أول من أشار إليه في كتابه "يوتوبيا"
more than 500 years ago.
قبل أكثر من 500 عام.
And its proponents have spanned the spectrum from the left to the right,
ويمتد أنصار هذه الخطة من اليسار إلى اليمين،
from the civil rights campaigner, Martin Luther King,
من الناشط في الحقوق المدنية مارتن لوثر كينغ
to the economist Milton Friedman.
إلى عالم الاقتصاد ميلتون فريدمان.
And it's an incredibly simple idea:
وهي فكرة بسيطة جداً:
basic income guarantee.
ضمان الدخل الأساسي.
What it is?
ما هذا؟
Well, that's easy.
الإجابة سهلة.
It's a monthly grant, enough to pay for your basic needs:
هي منحة شهرية تكفي لتأمين حاجاتك الأساسية:
food, shelter, education.
الطعام والمأوى والتعليم.
It's completely unconditional,
وهي غير مشروطة نهائياً،
so no one's going to tell you what you have to do for it,
فلن يطلب أحد منك شيئاً مقابلها،
and no one's going to tell you what you have to do with it.
ولن يوجهك أحد لكيفية استخدامها.
The basic income is not a favor, but a right.
فالدخل الأساسي ليس عبارة عن فضل، بل هو حق.
There's absolutely no stigma attached.
ولا يوجد له أية دلالة سلبية.
So as I learned about the true nature of poverty,
لذا عندما تعرفت على حقيقة الفقر
I couldn't stop wondering:
لم أستطع إلا أن أتعجب:
Is this the idea we've all been waiting for?
هل هذه الفكرة هي ما كنا ننتظر؟
Could it really be that simple?
هل يمكن أن تكون بهذه البساطة؟
And in the three years that followed,
وفي الثلاث السنوات التي تلت،
I read everything I could find about basic income.
قرأت كل ما وجدته عن الدخل الأساسي.
I researched the dozens of experiments
قمت بدراسة عشرات التجارب
that have been conducted all over the globe,
التي تم إجراؤها حول العالم،
and it didn't take long before I stumbled upon a story of a town
وسرعان ما عثرت على قصة بلدة
that had done it -- had actually eradicated poverty.
كانت قد قامت بذلك -- قامت فعلاً بالقضاء على الفقر.
But then ...
ولكن بعد ذلك ...
nearly everyone forgot about it.
نسيها الجميع تقريباً.
This story starts in Dauphin, Canada.
تبدأ هذه القصة في دوفين، كندا.
In 1974, everybody in this small town was guaranteed a basic income,
في 1974، تم ضمان دخل أساسي لكل سكان هذه البلدة الصغيرة،
ensuring that no one fell below the poverty line.
للتأكد ن أن لا يتدنى مستوى أحد تحت خط الفقر
At the start of the experiment,
في بداية التجربة،
an army of researchers descended on the town.
حط فريق من الباحثين في البلدة.
For four years, all went well.
وجرى كل شيء على مايرام لمدة أربع سنوات.
But then a new government was voted into power,
ولكن تم انتخاب حكومة جديدة،
and the new Canadian cabinet saw little point to the expensive experiment.
ولم يرى مجلس الوزراء الكندي الجديد جدوى من التجربة المكلفة.
So when it became clear there was no money left to analyze the results,
وعندما اتضح أنه لم يكن هناك مال كافٍ لتحليل النتائج،
the researchers decided to pack their files away in some 2,000 boxes.
قرر العلماء جمع ملفاتهم في حوالي 2000 صندوق.
Twenty-five years went by,
بعد 25 سنة،
and then Evelyn Forget, a Canadian professor,
قامت الأستاذة الكندية إيفيلين فور جي
found the records.
بإيجاد السجلات.
For three years, she subjected the data to all manner of statistical analysis,
خلال ثلاث سنوات، أخضعت البيانات لكل أنواع التحليل الإحصائي،
and no matter what she tried,
ومهما حاولت،
the results were the same every time:
كانت النتائج تبقى نفسها كل مرة:
the experiment had been a resounding success.
حققت هذه التجربة نجاحاً باهراً.
Evelyn Forget discovered
اكتشفت إيفيلين فور جي
that the people in Dauphin had not only become richer
أن أهل دوفين لم يصبحوا أغنى وحسب،
but also smarter and healthier.
بل أيضاً أذكى و بصحة أفضل.
The school performance of kids improved substantially.
تحسن أداء الأطفال في المدرسة بشكل ملحوظ.
The hospitalization rate decreased by as much as 8.5 percent.
وانخفض معدل دخول المستشفيات بنسبة 8.5%.
Domestic violence incidents were down,
تناقصت حوادث العنف الأسري
as were mental health complaints.
وشكاوى الصحة العقلية.
And people didn't quit their jobs.
ولم يترك الناس وظائفهم.
The only ones who worked a little less were new mothers and students --
الفئات الوحيدة التي عملت بشكل أقل هم الأمهات الجدد والطلاب --
who stayed in school longer.
الذين بقوا في المدرسة مدة أطول.
Similar results have since been found
منذ ذلك الحين، تم إيجاد نتائج مماثلة
in countless other experiments around the globe,
لعدد هائل من التجارب الأخرى حول العالم،
from the US to India.
من الولايات المتحدة حتى الهند.
So ...
لذا...
here's what I've learned.
هذا ما تعلمته.
When it comes to poverty,
عندما يتعلق الأمر بالفقر،
we, the rich, should stop pretending we know best.
يجب علينا، نحن الأغنياء، أن نكف عن الادعاء بأننا أكثر معرفة.
We should stop sending shoes and teddy bears to the poor,
يجب أن نكف عن إرسال الأحذية ودمى الدببة للفقراء،
to people we have never met.
لأشخاص لم يسبق والتقيناهم.
And we should get rid of the vast industry of paternalistic bureaucrats
ويجب أن نتخلص من القطاع الواسع من البيروقراطيين الأبويين
when we could simply hand over their salaries
حيث يمكن أن نمنح رواتبهم
to the poor they're supposed to help.
للفقراء ممن يجب أن يساعدوهم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Because, I mean, the great thing about money
أعني أن قيمة المال
is that people can use it to buy things they need
تكمن بقدرة الناس على شراء ما يحتاجون
instead of things that self-appointed experts think they need.
بدلاً من الأشياء التي يعتقد من نصّبوا أنفسهم خبراء أنهم يحتاجونها.
Just imagine how many brilliant scientists and entrepreneurs and writers,
تخيلوا كم عالماً وريادي أعمال وكاتباً لامعاً،
like George Orwell,
مثل جورج أورويل
are now withering away in scarcity.
يرزحون الآن تحت وطأة الفقر.
Imagine how much energy and talent we would unleash
تخيلوا كم سنحرر من الطاقات والمواهب
if we got rid of poverty once and for all.
إذا ما تخلصنا من الفقر نهائياً.
I believe that a basic income would work like venture capital for the people.
أعتقد أن الدخل الأساسي سيكون رأس مال استثمارياً للناس.
And we can't afford not to do it,
لا يمكننا تحمل نفقة ألا نقوم بهذا،
because poverty is hugely expensive.
لأن الفقر مكلف جداً.
Just look at the cost of child poverty in the US, for example.
لنلق نظرة على تكلفة فقر الأطفال في الولايات المتحدة مثلاً.
It's estimated at 500 billion dollars each year,
يقدّر هذا بـ500 مليار دولار كل عام،
in terms of higher health care spending, higher dropout rates,
من إنفاق أكبر على الرعاية الصحية، ونسبة أعلى من المتسربين،
and more crime.
وجرائم أكثر.
Now, this is an incredible waste of human potential.
وهذا هدر غير معقول للطاقات البشرية.
But let's talk about the elephant in the room.
لكن لنتحدث عن القضية التي يتم تجاهلها.
How could we ever afford a basic income guarantee?
كيف لنا أن نتحمل نفقة ضمان دخل أساسي؟
Well, it's actually a lot cheaper than you may think.
في الواقع إنه أرخص مما تتوقّع بكثير.
What they did in Dauphin is finance it with a negative income tax.
ما حدث في دوفين هو تمويلها بضريبة دخل سلبية.
This means that your income is topped up
هذا يعني تعويض النقص في دخلك
as soon as you fall below the poverty line.
حالما ينخفض مستواك تحت خط الفقر.
And in that scenario,
وفي ذاك السياق،
according to our economists' best estimates,
وفقاً لأفضل تفديرات علمائنا الاقتصاديين،
for a net cost of 175 billion --
بتكلفة صافية من 175 مليار --
a quarter of US military spending, one percent of GDP --
أي ربع الإنفاق العسكري في الولايات المتحدة وواحد بالمئة من إجمالي الناتج المحلي --
you could lift all impoverished Americans above the poverty line.
تستطيع أن ترفع مستوى كل الأميركيين الفقراء ليصبحوا فوق خط الفقر.
You could actually eradicate poverty.
تستطيع فعلاً أن تقضي على الفقر.
Now, that should be our goal.
هذا ما يجب أن يكون هدفنا الآن.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The time for small thoughts and little nudges is past.
مضى وقت الأفكار الصغيرة والدفعات البسيطة.
I really believe that the time has come for radical new ideas,
أعنقد أنه حان وقت الأفكار الجوهرية الجديدة
and basic income is so much more than just another policy.
والدخل الأساسي هو أكثر من مجرد خطة أخرى.
It is also a complete rethink of what work actually is.
كما أنه إعادة للنظر في المعنى الحقيقي للعمل.
And in that sense,
وفي هذا المعنى،
it will not only free the poor,
لن يتحرّر الفقراء فحسب،
but also the rest of us.
بل نحن أيضاً.
Nowadays, millions of people feel
حالياً، يشعر ملايين الناس
that their jobs have little meaning or significance.
بأن وظائفهم تفتقر للمعنى والأهمية.
A recent poll among 230,000 employees
يظهر استفتاء حديث بين 230.000 موظفاً
in 142 countries
في 142 دولة
found that only 13 percent of workers actually like their job.
أن نسبة 13% فقط من العمال يحبون عملهم.
And another poll found that as much as 37 percent of British workers
ووجد استفتاء آخر أن نسبة 37% من العمال البريطانيين
have a job that they think doesn't even need to exist.
يعتقدون أن وظائفهم بلا جدوى.
It's like Brad Pitt says in "Fight Club,"
كما يقول براد بيت في فيلم "نادي القتال"
"Too often we're working jobs we hate so we can buy shit we don't need."
"نعمل في وظائف نكرهها لنشتري تفاهات لا نحتاجها"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, don't get me wrong --
لا تسيئوا فهمي الآن --
I'm not talking about the teachers and the garbagemen
فأنا لا أتكلم عن المعلمين و عمال النظافة
and the care workers here.
و عمال الرعاية هنا.
If they stopped working,
إذا توقف هؤلاء عن العمل،
we'd be in trouble.
فسنكون في ورطة.
I'm talking about all those well-paid professionals with excellent résumés
لكني أتكلم عن أولئك الخبراء ذوي الرواتب العالية والسير الذاتية الممتازة
who earn their money doing ...
والذين يكسبون مالهم لدى القيام بـ...
strategic transactor peer-to-peer meetings
اجتماعات بين الأقران للعملاء الاستراتيجيين
while brainstorming the value add-on of disruptive co-creation
بينما يفكرون بإضافي القيمة للابتكار الهادم
in the network society.
في مجتمع الشبكات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Or something like that.
أو شيء من هذا القبيل.
Just imagine again how much talent we're wasting,
لنتخيل فقط كم نهدر من مواهب
simply because we tell our kids they'll have to "earn a living."
لأننا ببساطة نلقن أولادنا أن عليهم "كسب قوتهم"
Or think of what a math whiz working at Facebook lamented a few years ago:
أو لنفكر بما كان عبقري الرياضيات الذي يعمل لدى فيسبوك يندبه منذ عدة سنوات:
"The best minds of my generation
"أفضل العقول من أبناء جيلي
are thinking about how to make people click ads."
تفكر بكيفية جعل الناس يضغطون على الإعلانات."
I'm a historian.
أنا مؤرخ.
And if history teaches us anything,
وإذا كان التاريخ يعلمنا أي شيء
it is that things could be different.
فهو أن الأشياء قد تتغير.
There is nothing inevitable
لا يوجد شيء محتوم
about the way we structured our society and economy right now.
حول الطريقة التي شكّلنا فيها مجتمعنا واقتصادنا الآن.
Ideas can and do change the world.
الأفكار قادرة أن تغير العالم، وهي تقوم بذلك فعلاُ.
And I think that especially in the past few years,
وأعتقد أنه خاصة في السنوات القليلة الماضية
it has become abundantly clear
أصبح من الجلي بشكل كبير
that we cannot stick to the status quo --
أنه لا يمكننا التقيد بالوضع الراهن --
that we need new ideas.
بل نحن بحاجة أفكار جديدة.
I know that many of you may feel pessimistic
أعرف أن كثيراً منكم قد يكون متشائماً
about a future of rising inequality,
بمستقبل يعد بازدياد اللامساواة،
xenophobia
رهاب الأجانب،
and climate change.
والتغيرات المناخية.
But it's not enough to know what we're against.
لكن لا يكفي أن نعرف ما نقف ضده،
We also need to be for something.
يجب أن نكون مع شيء ما.
Martin Luther King didn't say, "I have a nightmare."
مارتن لوثر كينغ لم يقل "عندي كابوس."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He had a dream.
فقد كان عنده حلم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So ...
لذا...
here's my dream:
ها هو حلمي:
I believe in a future
أؤمن بمستقبل
where the value of your work is not determined
لا تتحدد فيه قيمة عملك
by the size of your paycheck,
بحجم راتبك،
but by the amount of happiness you spread
بل بكمية السعادة التي تنشرها
and the amount of meaning you give.
وكمية المعاني التي تهبها.
I believe in a future
أؤمن بمستقبل
where the point of education is not to prepare you for another useless job
لا يكون فيه هدف التعليم التحضير لوظائف أخرى بدون جدوى
but for a life well-lived.
بل لحياة سعيدة.
I believe in a future
أؤمن بمستقبل
where an existence without poverty is not a privilege
لا يكون فيه انعدام الفقر امتيازاً
but a right we all deserve.
بل حقاً نستحقه جميعاً.
So here we are.
ها نحن ذا.
Here we are.
ها نحن هنا.
We've got the research, we've got the evidence
لدينا البحث والدليل
and we've got the means.
ولدينا الوسيلة.
Now, more than 500 years after Thomas More first wrote about a basic income,
الآن وبعد أكثر من 500 عام على كتابة توماس مور للمرة الأولى عن الدخل الأساسي
and 100 years after George Orwell discovered the true nature of poverty,
و بعد 100 عام من اكتشاف جورج أورويل حقيقة الفقر
we all need to change our worldview,
يجب علينا أن نغير نظرتنا العالمية،
because poverty is not a lack of character.
لأن الفقر ليس نقصاً في الشخصية
Poverty is a lack of cash.
الفقر هو حاجة مادية.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)